<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes out of France: concerning great troubles likely to ensue, by occasion of the departure of the Queene Mother from Blois and the causes thereof. Contayned in the letters of the said Queene Mother, vnto her sonne the French King, and his answere therevnto; manifesting the motiues of his taking vp armes, and against whom he entends to imploy them. Dated the 17. of March, 1619. VVith foure other letters of the Queene Mother, to the Lord Chancelor, Keeper of the Seales; President Iannin, and Duke de Mayenne, and the Prince of Pyemont his letter vnto her, concerning these affaires. Faithfully translated, according to the French copie.</title>
            <author>Marie de Médicis, Queen, consort of Henry IV, King of France, 1573-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 15 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01170</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11284</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102585</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838357</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838357</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2732</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01170)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2732)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1137:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes out of France: concerning great troubles likely to ensue, by occasion of the departure of the Queene Mother from Blois and the causes thereof. Contayned in the letters of the said Queene Mother, vnto her sonne the French King, and his answere therevnto; manifesting the motiues of his taking vp armes, and against whom he entends to imploy them. Dated the 17. of March, 1619. VVith foure other letters of the Queene Mother, to the Lord Chancelor, Keeper of the Seales; President Iannin, and Duke de Mayenne, and the Prince of Pyemont his letter vnto her, concerning these affaires. Faithfully translated, according to the French copie.</title>
                  <author>Marie de Médicis, Queen, consort of Henry IV, King of France, 1573-1642.</author>
                  <author>Louis XIII, King of France, 1601-1643.</author>
                  <author>Savoie, Victor-Amé, duc de, 1587-1637.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8; 4, 18 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] S[nodham] for Nathanael Newbery, and are to bee sould at his shop vnder S. Peters Church in Cornehill, and in Popes-head Alley at the signe of the Star,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1619.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Evidently a translation of one of several French editions of the same year.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>"The Queene Mothers first letter, sent vnto the King of France, her sonne, from Loche, the 23. of February, 1619. stilo nouo" begins new register and pagination; within this register, "A letter written by the King of France, in answere to a letter sent by the Queene his mother, bearing date the 17. of March 1619. stilo nouo" has separate dated title page and pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIII, 1610-1643 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2732:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Newes out of France:</hi> Concerning great troubles likely to enſue, by occaſion of the departure of the Queene Mother from <hi>Blois:</hi> And the cauſes thereof.</p>
                  <p>Contayned in the Letters of the ſaid Queene Mother, vnto her Sonne the <hi>French</hi> KING, and his Anſwere therevnto; manifeſting the Motiues of his taking vp Armes, and againſt whom he entends to imploy them. Dated the 17. of <hi>March,</hi> 1619.</p>
                  <p>VVith foure other Letters of the Queene Mother, to the Lord Chancelor, Keeper of the <hi>Seales; Preſident</hi> Iannin, <hi>and Duke</hi> de Mayenne, and the Prince of <hi>Pyemont</hi> his Letter vnto her, concerning theſe Affaires.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Faithfully tranſlated, according to the French Copie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T.S.</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Newbery,</hi> and are to bee ſould at his ſhop vnder S. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in Cornchill, and in Popes-head Alley at the ſigne of the Star. 1619.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2732:2"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:2732:2"/>
                  <head>THE QVEENE Mothers firſt Letter, ſent vnto the King of <hi>France,</hi> her Sonne, from <hi>Loche,</hi> 
                     <date>the 23. of <hi>February,</hi> 1619. <hi>Stile nouo.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lord my Sonne. I haue long ſuffered &amp; endured my honor and liberty to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, and withall concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued many ſtrong and ſtrange apprehenſions of the danger of my life, and that which moſt fencibly moued me thereunto, was the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priuation of your ſight and preſence. All which in ſome ſort and manner being done vnder the authority of your name; with the like patience I would haue expected &amp; attended the future euent thereof, without (for mine owne part) once ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to know whether your proceedings and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires be well or badly led: but being (to my great grief)
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2732:3"/>to preach and ſet forth your vertues, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable praiſes, in ſuch a place wherein you ſhall thinke good, that I ſhall continue the reſt of my dayes. Beſeeching God (as continually I doe, with the moſt paſſionate feeling of my heart) for the proſperity of you, and all your kingdome, being moſt truely, euen in the vttermoſt degree of fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and affection, my good Lord and Sonne.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt affectioned Mother and Subiect MARIA.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From Loche,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>the</hi> 23. <hi>of February,</hi> 1619. <hi>Stilo nouo.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:2732:3"/>
                  <head>THE LETTER Written by the Queene Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſent from <hi>Angouleſme</hi> to the King of <hi>France:</hi> Bearing date the 10. of <hi>March</hi> 1619. <hi>Stilo nouo.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lord, and deare Sonne, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that no man will approue the counſell that hath beene giuen vnto you, to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine tenne dayes from returning an anſwere vnto my Letters, and then to put mee in a doubt how to vnderſtand your intentions, which to be borrowed from others, and none of yours,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2732:4"/>I doe too much conceiue and apprehend, by the great numbers of Commiſſions, which are ſent forth vnder your Name to renforce and to leuie new companies of foot, and troupes of horſe, by the Switzers, which are ſaid to be ſent for, by the Cannons which are reported to be already mounted and ſet forward out of your Arſenall, and by the munitions of warre which are ſent againſt mee; I moſt humbly intreate you my Lord and deare Sonne, for a while to ſtay your proceedings, and withall to conſider, what you are by others moued to doe.</p>
                  <p>When I writ that I deſired to be ſo much oblieged vnto you, as that I might let you vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand and know ſuch things ſpecially as import the good and furtherance of your ſeruice and eſtate, and to belocue that the extremitie of the griefe which I conceaue for the armes and forces which you are counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to leuye, at this preſent doth in a manner kill mee. The ſtaine which is giuen to your name in all ages of a prodigious violence, and the deſolation of your people, which thereby will enſue, will doe you more wrong, then death can procure vnto me, in ſuch manner, that proſtrating my ſelfe at your feete; I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2732:4"/>you, and earneſtly intreate you, ſpeede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to countermaund all your aforeſaid prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of forces and armies now levyed, which are bent onely againſt mee, what ſhew ſoeuer is otherwiſe made &amp; pretended, ſeeing they are preſently levyed vpon my departure from <hi>Blois,</hi> and that it is euidently knowne, that at this preſent you haue no other occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ciuill or forraigne warre to moue you thereunto: And therefore once againe I ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly intreate you to giue eare vnto me; If my intent and determination had no other ground then onely a deſire to be freed of cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuitie, I thinke and certainely beleeue that no man could diſlike it; there being no law in the world, (no not among the Barbarians) which prohibiteth Priſoners to ſeeke for their libertie, and to ſecure their liues.</p>
                  <p>But ſeeing that I neuer had, nor yet haue, any intent or meaning but to let you know and be made acquainted with the euident danger of your affaires, as alſo of your good Subiects, eaſily to be perceiued, by the with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing of your perſon and your counſell from the greateſt and moſt noble perſonages of your realme; I am vndoubtedly perſwaded, that your bountie would gladly haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2732:5"/>the paſſion of my zeale, and withall commended the fidelitie and reſpect which I ought to haue, and owe vnto you, if it were not violently diuerted by thoſe, who diſdai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning all the offers of amitie and good will, which in conſideration of you, I haue made vnto them, hazard the ſtate, and trouble the peace and tranquillity thereof, being per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that they cannot build the miracle of their fortunes, but vpon my ruine, whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to I would gladly conſent, if thereby I might further and procure the continuance of your greatneſſe.</p>
                  <p>I proteſt before God and his holy Angells, that for mine owne part, I pretend nothing, neither haue any other deſigne then that which I ought to haue, for the proſperitie of your raigne &amp; kingdome: and for that I ſee &amp; manifeſtly perceiue your eares to be ſtopped againſt my faithfull and iuſt ſupplications, I muſt and ſhall be conſtrained, preſently to make knowne in all places both of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Europe,</hi> and hereafter vnto your ſelfe, the true proofes of my ſinceritie and innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, aſſuring you, that as much as I can, I will ſeeke meanes to impeach and hinder the force of armes, whereunto you are drawne,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2732:5"/>not onely againſt the law of God, but alſo of the whole world, and Nature, cauſing the great perſonages of your Monarchie, offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and diſcontented, to breake their bounds and to doe as much againſt the obedience whereunto (as it is well knowne) I alwaies counſelled them: But for mine owne part, I will in all places, vſe my libertie and my life to pleaſe and content you, but yet to oppoſe my ſelfe againſt the crueltie of thoſe that go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, if for the ſpace of this whole weeke I perceiue and ſee the continuance of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt forces, which at this preſent are prepared, contrary to that which I hope to finde in your good nature, and the equity of my cauſe, which I expect from God; I thinke I ſhall be forced by my iuſt and generall complaints, to publiſh and make knowne, that my deplo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable misfortunes continually encreaſe by vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt and ſuperfluous exceſſe of the ambitions and feares of thoſe that ſoueraignely poſſeſſe your perſon and Kingdome: and that as by your permiſſion, (but yet with my moſt great diſpleaſure and diſlike) I ought to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe my actions to the neceſſities of defence, alwayes contayning my ſelfe ſo religiouſly within the bounds thereof, that I may onely
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2732:6"/>draw you from an opinion of diſlike, for gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing mee leaue to ſuppreſſe them, that ſo I may preſerue my life, and the long dayes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on earth, which I aſſure my ſelfe you will and wiſh vnto her, which is, and euer ſhall bee, whatſoeuer happeneth, my Lord and deare Sonne,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your moſt humble and moſt affectioned Mother and Subiect MARIA.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From Angouleſme,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>the</hi> 10. <hi>of March,</hi> 1619. <hi>Stilo nouo.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2732:6"/>
                  <p>A LETTER Written by the King of <hi>France,</hi> in Anſwere to a Letter ſent by the Queene his Mother, bearing date the 17. of March 1619. <hi>Stilo nouo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Faithfully tranſlated, according to the French Copie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T.S.</hi> for <hi>Nathanael Newbery,</hi> and are to bee ſould at his ſhop vnder S. <hi>Peters</hi> Church in Cornehill, and in Popes-head Alley at the ſigne of the Star. 1619.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2732:7"/>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:2732:7"/>
                  <head>A LETTER, Written by the <hi>KJNG</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> in anſwere to a Letter ſent by the Queene his Mother, bearing date <date>the 17. of March 1619. <hi>Stilo nouo.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>ADAME.</hi> Your laſt Letters, as alſo the firſt that I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued from you, are to mee aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that it reſteth not in your power to write and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie vnto mee the true feeling of your Interiour cogitations, touching your opinion concerning the gouernement of mine eſtate. You know and may perſwade your ſelfe, that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:2732:8"/>the ſame neither can, nor may, in any ſort be blamed or diſliked, but that the diſgrace thereof muſt needes fall, and ſpecially be laide vpon my ſelfe: which moueth mee to thinke, and verily perſwades me, that you will not offer me that wrong, to bereaue me of the glory of my raigne, by attributing vnto me the reputation not to doe or effect any thing, but by the motions of others.</p>
                  <p>I know there are ſome that not onely ſeeke the meanes to perſwade you, yea, and to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>print in your minde an euill opinion of my affaires, but alſo inforce themſelues to mooue you to apprehend, and ſiniſterly to coniecture of the preparations to Warre, which at this preſent I make, as if I had an intent or meaning to vſe them againſt you. But although my authoritie of a King, doth diſpence with, and warrant mee not to yeeld an accompt of mine actions vnto any man, but onely to God; Neuertheleſſe, I would that all the world ſhould know, that my re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution and intent is, to imploy them, onely for the maintenance of mine owne authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the peace and tranquility of my King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and to hinder and impeach the meanes and motions, that in any wiſe may or might trouble the ſame, or procure the Ruine and deſolation of my faithfull Subiects, as alſo
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:2732:8"/>to oppoſe my ſelfe againſt the pernicious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents purpoſes and practiſes of thoſe, who vnder your name and title, haue levyed and gathered diuers companies of Souldiers, as well within, as without the Realme, which I ſhould neuer haue beleeued, if I had not ſeene and heard the Letters, which they haue cauſed you to write, not onely touching this ſubiect, but alſo to giue an euill impreſſion, of the adminiſtration of my affaires vnto di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Princes, Lords, and others, as well my Subiects as ſtrangers, who would not beleeue it. The knowledge and feeling (which the perturbators of the common peace of this Realme haue alwaies had,) of the ſingular affection and honour which I beare vnto you, makes them hope that my clemency will indifferently pardon and remit all the attempts which they enterpriſe and take on them to doe in your name, againſt my regall authoritie.</p>
                  <p>But I alwayes knew, and know how to diſtinguiſh your intereſt from theirs, in mee, hauing no other reſolution, then onely to loue and honour you as my Mother, and to puniſh them as rebellious Subiects, and ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes to my eſtate. Nature ſo powerfully vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth mee to harken vnto all that which in any wiſe toucheth and concerneth your
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2732:9"/>good or hurt, that I am bound to imploy all the power and force that God hath giuen vnto mee, for your deliuerance. Thoſe that attend vpon my perſon, haue ſo many and ſo euident teſtimonies to perſwade them of the reſpect which I alwaies haue had and borne vnto you, that you may beleeue, and certaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſwade your ſelfe, that they are as deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous of your contentment, as in reaſon they are affected, to further and aduance thoſe things that concerne and appertaine vnto my ſeruice. The former teſtimony as alſo thoſe which continually they ſhew vnto me there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, are ſo euident, that they binde and obliege mee to maintaine and protect them, both by reaſon and Iuſtice.</p>
                  <p>Aſſure your ſelfe, MADAME, that there is no man ſo bolde, that dare enterpriſe or take vpon him to propound any propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which may in any wiſe ſound againſt, or be contrary to the Honour and reſpect which is due vnto you. If you perſwade your ſelfe, that there is any thing to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired and deſired in a Kingdome, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Iuſtice and Peace hath equally flouriſhed and beene maintained, euer ſince I had the care and gouernement thereof, you may when it pleaſeth you, vtter vnto mee that which you ſecretly conceiue in your minde,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2732:9"/>without ſpreading, or cauſing Complaints publikely to bee giuen foorth: Which man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of proceeding, as it is wholy againſt my meaning and intent, ſo it giues cauſe ſiniſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to iudge of yours; for that the ſame hath neuer beene nor is practiſed or vſed, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by thoſe that alwayes haue had a deſire, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to perturbe and trouble the gouernment, than to procure the reformation thereof.</p>
                  <p>In my laſt Letters I wrote, and likewiſe by <hi>Mounſieur de Bethune,</hi> by word of mouth certified vnto you, that if it pleaſe you, you may chuſe any of your owne Houſes, or of mine, therein to liue at your pleaſure and full and free liberty, without any impeach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; in ſuch manner that it is long of your ſelfe, if you liue not happily and contented<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Let mee onely entreate at your hands, to be ayding and aſſiſtant vnto my good enten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, with a true correſpondence of will &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; and let me ſee and perceiue ſome teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies from you therein, as worthy of a good Mother, as thoſe which you ſhall receiue from me, are worthy of him, who</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>MADAME,</salute> 
                     <signed>reſteth your moſt humble and obedient Sonne LOVYS.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From Paris,</hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>the</hi> 17. <hi>of March,</hi> 1619. <hi>Stilo nouo.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="letters">
                  <pb facs="tcp:2732:10"/>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2732:10"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Letters written by the Queene</hi> Mother of France, to the Lord Chancellor, the Lord Keeper of the Seales, and the Lord Preſident I annin.</head>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>The Queenes Letter to the Lord Chancellour.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Lord, I haue hitherto laboured and ſought only to let the King my Sonne vnderſtand, the iuſt cauſes and reaſons of my eſcape from <hi>Blois,</hi> wholly grounded vpon the paſſion, and bounden duty which I haue and owe vnto the good and furtherance of his ſeruice. But to the contrary, thoſe that are and attend about his Perſon, thinke me ſo vnworthy to know his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, that they haue made me deferre the ſame, and induced him to rigorous and violent cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ſuch as the like were neuer heard of before; as thoſe which I ſpecially apprehend, which are to raiſe puiſſant forces againſt the perſon of her, that brought him into the World; and who breathes and apprehends no other thing, but onely paſſion and obedience, to thoſe things which may be good &amp; profitable vnto him, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the place and preſence of euill counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, were contrary, and ſuſpitious vnto mee. <hi>Villiers</hi> hath not forborne in heart, to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the tender affection of nature, in ſuch manner, that I muſt of force with more hope, ſummon you before God, and your natiue
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:2732:11"/>Country; that according to the duty of your office, you ſhould not feare to ſhew vnto him, the great importance and danger of that which he is moned to doe: without any reſpect at all of my dignity, or commiſeration of my miſery. And to the end that you may truly know and vnderſtand, what I haue written vnto him, I haue deliuered vnto this bearer two Coppies of the Letters which I ſent him touching this matter, as knowing well, that they are often times kept from you, and all others the good and ancient Counſellours and Seruants to the King and the Crowne. And herewith I beſeech God, my Lord Chancellour, to protect and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue you.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>From <hi>Angouleſme</hi> 
                           <date>the 10. of <hi>March,</hi> 1619. <hi>Stilo nouo.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>The Queenes Letter to the Lord Keeper of the Seales.</head>
                     <p>MY Lord: It was neuer yet heard of, not knowne, that a Prince would at any time purpoſely defer and put off the hearing of the counſell or ſuite of a faithfull Subiect, and that a Sonne, in ſtead of ſatisfying the ſincere affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a good Mother, ſhould bee moued, or counſelled, violently to take armes againſt her, therewith to oppreſſe her. I know well that the wiſdome wherewith you are ſo religiouſly in dowed, neither will nor can moue you to giue him any ſuch counſell; and much leſſe can I bee
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2732:11"/>perſwaded, that the good nature of the King my ſonne, can be induced or moued vnto any ſuch extraordinary motions, whereof if I were in doubt, the very greefe I ſhould therby conceue would kill mee. But ſeeing that God hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently made mee to perceiue and know the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent natures, of thoſe that alwaies were my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and ſeeke to afflict me: I thought good to put you herewith in mind of the ſtrict dutie whereunto you are obliged; which is, freely to tell him your minde and opinion, in ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant a cauſe. And reading the Coppies of two Letters written by me vnto him touching this matter, you may iudge and eaſily perceiue the equity and true intent of my deſeruing: which that you may the better conſider of, I beſeech God (my Lord) to haue you in his keeping.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>From <hi>Angouleſme</hi> 
                           <date>the 10. of <hi>March,</hi> 1619. <hi>Stilo nouo.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>The Queenes Letter to the Lord Preſident Iannin.</head>
                     <p>MY Lord, my deſire is, that you ſhould tell the King my Sonne, that which in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence you thinke conuenient and fit for him to beleeue and to do, touching the ſupplication by mee made vnto him; to hearken vnto the great paſſion which at this preſent I haue for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſernation of his authority, and the good of his eſtate: for that your Office, and your counſels at this preſent are much more neceſſary and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2732:12"/>convenienter for him then euer they were, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that hee is moued vnto the moſt violent &amp; vnlawfull warre that euer was heard of. I writ vnto him another Letter, whereof, as alſo of the firſt, this bearer ſhall giue you a copy, to the end that being informed of the iuſtice and cleerenes of my proceedings, you may giue him counſell as much as poſſibly you can, for the good and furtherance of his ſeruice, and the peace of his Kingdome, which I will ſeeke to maintaine as much as in melieth, euen to the loſſe of my life; and ſo I beſeech God my Lord to haue you in his holy keeping.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>From <hi>Angouleſme</hi> 
                           <date>the 10. of March, 1619. <hi>Stilo nouo.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>The Queenes Letter to the Duke de Mayenne.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y good Coſen, I was reſolued for euer with patience to haue furmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted my afflictions, as long as there had beene no other queſtion made but of my intereſt and paines, thereby not to miniſter any cauſe or ſhadow vnto the King my Sonne, that I once ſo much as imagined or dreamt of a deſire to ſeparate my ſelfe from his intents, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it is to be thought, that therein he is bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly counſelled: but hauing for the ſpace of a whole yeere beene ſolicited by the generall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints and intreaties of diuers perſons, both within and without the Realme, to let the King
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2732:12"/>my Sonne vnderſtand and know the eminent danger of his authority, and the tranquility of his Realme; I made no difficulty to hazard my life by a moſt dangerous eſcape, that ſo I may ſafely ſhew him the intent and true meaning of a good and faithfull Mother; and hau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> already written vnto him, moſt humbly beſeeching him to ſet mee downe ſuch a forme as it ſhall pleaſe him to appoint mee to hold and obſerue in the vttering thereof. I thought good ſpeedily to impart thus much vnto you, not onely becauſe the account I make of you, together with all <hi>France,</hi> makes mee deſire to let you vnderſtand my determination: but alſo knowing the great eſtimation which the King my Sonne hath, and ought to haue of your Counſell; I wiſh you would ioyne your intreaties with mine, thereby to moue him vnto the remedies, which I aſſure my ſelfe you know better then others to bee moſt neceſſary. Strictly intreating you aboue all things, as much as poſſibly I may, in the meane time carefully to put to your helping hand, that no ſtirre be made; and that euery man attend and expect from his good nature that which he is obliged to ſhew vnto his Subiects and eſtate. If I needed any witneſſes to proue, that the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of the ſeruice of the King my Sonne haue moued me to certaine reſolutions, which no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concerned mine owne particular, I would firſt ſet you downe for one; and at this preſent I proteſt vnto you, vpon the confidence which I
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2732:13"/>deſire to haue of your magnanimity, in a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſuch importance; and in reſpect of the inclination, which you know well I alwayes bare vnto you, that in the moſt interior thoughts of my heart, I haue no other intents nor reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, then onely thoſe, which the proſperity and power of the King my Sonne cauſe me to haue. Let vs therefore labour to that end, and for your part you ſhall finde mee (together with the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count I make of your valour) to be alwayes</p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>From <hi>Roche Rezay</hi> 
                           <date>the 6. of March 1619.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>Your very good and affectionate Coſen, <hi>MARIA.</hi>
                        </signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>The Duke de Mayennes Anſwer to the Queenes Letter.</head>
                     <p>MAdam: I cannot conceale from your Maieſty, the extreame diſpleaſure that I feele in my ſelfe, to ſee and behold the eſtate whereunto your departure from <hi>Blois</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and bring the affaires of this Realme: And ſhould conceiue much more, were it not for the aſſurance which it pleaſeth you in honor to giue me, of your true intents, for the good and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment of the King. I beſeech God with all my heart, (Madam) that he would be pleaſed to ayde you with holy inſpirations. For mine own part, hauing not the meanes to contribute any other thing thereunto, but that which belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to the duty of an honeſt man, a moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2732:13"/>Seruant to the King, and one that reſolutely hath determined (all other conſiderations ſet apart) wholly and onely to relie vpon his will and pleaſure: Doe me that Honor in the meane time, good Madam, to beleeue that I am</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Your moſt humble and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ſeruant, <hi>De. Mayenne.</hi>
                        </signed>
                        <dateline>From <hi>Burdeaux</hi> 
                           <date>the 12. of <hi>March,</hi> 1619. <hi>Stilo nouo.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <div type="letter">
                     <head>A Letter written by the Prince of Piemont to the Queene.</head>
                     <p>MAdam: I haue conceiued an exceeding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment, to accompany my moſt Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Lord the King, in his pretended voyage to <hi>Blois,</hi> to viſit your Maieſty, in hope there to to haue had the meanes to haue done you ſome ſeruice; perſwading my ſelfe, that the enteruiew of your Maieſties, reeſtabliſhing a perfect vnion between you, as we here ſaw, noted and percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by all ſorts of good diſpoſitions, I ſhould haue had a better meanes, by my ſubmiſſion and obedience to teſtifie and ſhew forth, how much I eſteeme of the Honor to bee allied vnto the ſame. But how much the more I reioyced in the expectation and attendance of that good happe, ſo much the more greefe I receiued and conceiued at the diſpleaſure I tooke to ſee my ſelfe eſtranged and prolonged from it, by the ſudden and vnexpected departure of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2732:14"/>from thence: And that which greeued me more, was, to ſee and perceiue by your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties Letters, that you haue taken occaſion to withdraw your perſon from <hi>Blois,</hi> ſuppoſing your ſelfe therein not to be ſecure, and that you could not freely let the King know of the diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders which ſome men haue made you beleeue to be crept into his eſtate. Which I eſteem not to proceede from the pure will or conceit of your Maieſty, whoſe iudgement and nature is moſt excellent, but onely from the craft and pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie of thoſe, who ſeeing and perceiuing your Maieſtie to ſtand vpon the point of ſtrict vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting together, haue giuen you thoſe impreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, hoping to reape profit by your diſunion, and the trouble which they peraduenture ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it will breede vnto this ſtate: for it is moſt certaine, and I am able to iuſtifie it, as hauing known it well; that there was not any kinde of liberty whatſoeuer, which your Maieſty ſhould not haue had in <hi>Blois;</hi> and that there cannot be any more added to the tender motions, and true affection, which the King beareth vnto you, if we marke and conſider the conduction of his ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, both priuate and publike, which all are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the moſt great reputation which hee hath gotten, and to the eſtimation in all places made of his vertue and generoſity, whereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the effects which all Chriſtendome feeleth, I daily ſee and perceiue diuers manifeſt proofes, beholding him ſitting in the middle of the anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2732:14"/>Officers and Counſellors of the late King his Father, with ſo ſolide a iudgement, ſo exact Iuſtice, and ſo firme and couragious reſolution, that there is no man but will iudge (and ſhal find ſubiect to admire him, and to beleeue) that God hath endued him with ſo many excellent parts, with an intent to bleſſe his Raigne, and to raiſe and eleuate his glory, aboue that of his Aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors. The profeſſion that I haue alwayes made to loue the truth, the duty which bindeth me to publiſh that which I know, and the extreame griefe I conceiue to behold the labyrinth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>into (thoſe which in ſome manner diſguiſe the ſame vnto you) would caſt you, ſhall diſpence with me, if it pleaſe you Madam, for ſpeaking ſo freely vnto you. And further, if I beſeech you, (as I doe) with all humility, to baniſh out of your thoughts all whatſoeuer you may haue imagined or conceiued therein, to the preiudice of the ſincerity of the Kings intents, and of his Graces prudent and wiſe conduction. Aſſuring my ſelfe, that when it ſhall pleaſe your Maieſty to looke better into it, without ſuſpition, you ſhall therein find all ſorts of ſatisfactions; ſeeing that like a good and a wiſe Mother you cannot haue any greater deſire then to behold the proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity of the King your Sonnes affaires, and to liue in perfect loue and amity with him. I know he is much moued againſt thoſe, whom he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueth and eſteemeth to haue a pretence, vnder your name to moue and procure an alteration;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2732:15"/>and I perceiue that he maketh preparation pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully to aſſayle them. It conſiſteth in your wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome Madam, to preuent the infinite miſchiefs that thereby may ariſe, and not to endure nor ſee by your occaſion, and vnder pretence to procure another order in the State, confuſion; and thoſe diſorders therein to reigne, which commonly follow and enſue ciuill warres, God, nature, your owne good, and all ſorts of conſiderations bind you thereunto; I aſſure and perſwade my ſelfe that the bounty, and good nature of your Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie will wholly moue you to the contrary. The Houſe of <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>oy,</hi> and my ſelfe ſpecially, are ſo much beholding vnto the King, that in caſe to preſerue his authority, to bring and compell the enemies of the quiet eſtate of <hi>France,</hi> and the greatneſſe of his Crowne, to reaſon and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and to reſtore your Maieſty to the liberty which you are bereaued of, by your retract from <hi>Blois,</hi> hee ſhall bee conſtrained to make warre, we will therein freely venture our liues &amp; goods, and all our forces to teſtifie to the World that we are not vnthankfull for the vnſpeakable fauours which it hath pleaſed him to impart vnto vs; herewith beſeeching God long to preſerue your Maieſty in health, and to giue mee Madam by my good endeuours and ſeruices, the quality<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </p>
                     <closer>
                        <dateline>From <hi>Paris</hi> 
                           <date>the 12. of March, 1619.</date>
                        </dateline>
                        <signed>
                           <hi>To be your moſt humble and moſt obedient ſeruant,</hi> V. Amedee.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </div>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2732:15"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
